In the last lecture I talked about guards, now I want you to consider for for a case so that we're accessing
Son konumada Garth's Now' konutuk ve bilinmeyen bir rotaya eriebilmek iin bir
a route which is unknown.
dava iin dnecektim.
We actually saw one way of handling it with redirect here because if we try to access new posts when
Aslnda bunu ynlendirme ile ele almann bir yolunu grdk nk kimlii dorulanmadnda yeni
unauthenticated, this route is unknown because it's not rendered
yaynlara erimeye alrsak bu yol ilenmedii iin bilinmiyordu.
and as you could see if we still click on new post, we are essentially redirected back to post.
Ve grebildiin gibi yine de yeni postay tklarsak, aslnda postaya geri ynlendiriliriz.
This is one way of handling for 404 requests,
Bu drt istek iin bir yoludur.
you can simply redirect to another route.
Baka bir rotaya ynlendirebilirsiniz.
However you can also handle them in a different way,
Ancak bunlar farkl bir ekilde de halledebilirsiniz.
if you want to handle them differently I have to comment this out, otherwise this will catch any unknown
Onlar farkl ekilde ele almak isterseniz, yorumlamam lazm, bilinmeyen herhangi bir
requests.
istei yakalayacaktr.
You can specify the route component here and if you leave out the path so you don't add path, you can
Burada rota bileenini belirleyebilirsiniz ve yol eklemediinizden yolu terk ederseniz, yol eklemediinizde, bilinmeyen herhangi
simply define a component or the render method you learned about to render something for any unknown route.
bir rota iin bir ey oluturmay rendiiniz bir bileen veya ileme yntemi basite tanmlayabilirsiniz.
So here I'm going to output not found,
Yani burada ben bulunamadm iin dklyorum.
of course you could again just set it, use component and render 404 error page component you created
Tabii ki yine sadece bileeni kullandklarn ve oluturduunuz hata sayfas bileeni iin 0 deerini verdiini syleyebilirdiniz,
but this route will catch any routes which are not handled prior to it.
ancak bu rota daha nce ele alnmayan tm rotalar yakalayacak.
So any unknown routes in our case and it will output this.
Durumumuzda hi bilinmeyen yollar var ve bunu ktlyoruz.
Now it won't work together with redirecting from the root route because this also catches all and
Artk, rota rotasndan ynlendirme yapmakla birlikte almayacaktr, nk hepsi bizi yakalamak iin ve hangisinin bir
what ever order you use, one or the other wins
veya daha fazla galibini kullandnz emrediyor.
so the other one doesn't do anything. For any other use cases where you don't redirect from the route
Dolaysyla dieri, gzergah rotasndan ynlendirme yapmadnz dier kullanm durumlar iin hibir
route though,
ey yapmaz.
you can use them together.
Bunlar birlikte kullanabilirsiniz.
But here this is a nice catch all route which should always come last and show an appropriate page or
Ancak burada, bu, her zaman en son gelip uygun bir sayfay gsterecek veya bilinmeyen yollar iin baz kukla
render some dummy content for unknown routes,
ierik oluturmas gereken gzel bir yol yakalamaktr.
let me show this to you. If we now click on new post which is unknown because we're not rendering that
size gstermeyim, nk kimlii dorulanmam olmas nedeniyle bu rota bileenini oluturmuyoruz.
route component due to us not being authenticated,
imdi, bilinmeyen yeni yayna tklarsak bunu
we see not found. The same for the route URL by the way,
Uzaklatrdnz yolda ayn eyi bulamadn gryoruz.
there we also see not found because it's not defined right now,
Orada hepimiz grmedik, nk u anda tanmlanmam.
posts still works though.
Yaynlar yine de alyor.
So this is a catch all route,
Yani bu, tm rota yakalamaktr.
another important concept especially for 404 cases to catch any unknown routes.
zellikle 4 vaka iin bilinmeyen dier rotalar yakalamak iin bir baka nemli konsept.
Now as I said, it won't work together with redirect if you redirect from slash, if you redirect from any
imdi dediim gibi, herhangi bir hata sayfasndan yn bulursanz ve eik izgi izgiden ynlendirirseniz ynlendirme
error page than slash,
ile birlikte almaz.
it'll work though.
Geri ie yarayacak.
The reason they don't work together is that here, from is treated as a prefix and therefore this catches
Birlikte almamalarnn nedeni, gelen duyunun bir nek olarak ele alnmas ve bu
all routes as does this and therefore no matter how you order them, it won't work together.
nedenle bize istedii tm gzergahlar yakalamas ve dolaysyla nasl sipari ederseniz gidin birlikte almayacadr.
I still wanted to show you both because you rarely have the case that two routes collide here and then
Hala hem sana gstermek istedim, nk burada iki gzergahn arpt nadiren vuku buluyorsun ve o zaman
you have a powerful way of handling 404 error cases with a route without a path.
drt ya da drt an yollar olmayan bir rota ile uramann gl bir yolunu buluyorsun.